Joe Friday Collection on the U.S.S. Huron PC.5038
State Archives of North Carolina
Joe Friday Collection on the U.S.S. Huron
1984-1989
PC.5038
Manuscripts
0.410
Joe Friday was a graduate student in East Carolina University's program in maritime history and nautical archeology who researched and mapped the wreck of the U.S.S. Huron in the late 1980s. This research culminated in Friday's master's thesis, A History of the Wreck of the U.S.S. Huron, in 1988. The Joe Friday Collection on the U.S.S. Huron, 1984-1989, primarily consists of research materials gathered by Friday while conducting his research, as well as drafts, notes, and other materials related to the thesis itself.
Friday, Joe D., Jr.
Outer Banks History Center
Box Box 1
Gift
Arrangement
Alphabetical.
Access Restrictions
Available for research.
Biographical/Historical
The U.S.S. Huron was an iron-hulled screw steamer of the United States Navy. She was built in the mid-1870s and commissioned at Philadelphia Navy Yard in 1875. She was stationed at Norfolk Navy Yard and cruised the Caribbean and Gulf of Mexico for two years before returning for repairs in August 1877. She ran aground in November 1877 during a storm off the coast of Nags Head, North Carolina. 98 passengers were killed when she heeled over. The wreck of the Huron is now a popular diving site, located about 250 yards offshore at 35.97751, -75.63092. Joe Friday, a graduate student in East Carolina University's program in maritime history and nautical archeology, researched and mapped the wreck of the Huron in the late 1980s. This research culminated in Friday's master's thesis, A History of the Wreck of the U.S.S. Huron, submitted to the university in 1988.
Joe D. Friday, Jr.
Custodial History
Formerly classified as 33MSS-0-61
Scope and Content
The Joe Friday Collection on the U.S.S. Huron, 1984-1989, primarily consists of research materials gathered by Friday while writing his master's thesis on the wreck of the U.S.S. Huron in the late 1980s. The research materials in this collection were photocopied by Friday from libraries and archival repositories; no original manuscripts pertinent to the ship are present. Folder titles include dates of the original documents in parentheses when known. Also included are drafts, notes, an outline and prospectus, and other materials created by Friday while writing his thesis.
Huron (Screw steamer)
Shipwrecks--North Carolina--Nags Head; Underwater archaeology--North Carolina
- Annotated Bibliography Notecards, circa 1987; 38925; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Annotated Bibliography Notecards)
- Articles and Publications (1879-1981), circa 1986; 38926; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Articles and Publications (1879-1981))
- Government Documents (1866-1975), circa 1986; 38927; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Government Documents (1866-1975))
- A History of the Wreck of the U.S.S. Huron by Joe Friday, circa 1988; 38928; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder A History of the Wreck of the U.S.S. Huron by Joe Friday)
- A History of the Wreck of the U.S.S. Huron by Joe Friday: Draft, 1988; 38929; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder A History of the Wreck of the U.S.S. Huron by Joe Friday: Draft)
- Images (1877-1980s), circa 1986; 38930; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Images (1877-1980s))
- Logbook Index Cards, circa 1987; 38931; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Logbook Index Cards)
- Manuscripts (1876-1899), 1987; 38932; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Manuscripts (1876-1899))
- Maps (1983-1987), circa 1987; 38933; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Maps (1983-1987))
- Notes, circa 1986-1989; 38934; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Notes)
- Outline and Prospectus, 1986; 38935; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Outline and Prospectus)
- Research Correspondence and Call Slips, 1984-1988; 38936; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Research Correspondence and Call Slips)
- Ship Plans (1876-1980s), circa 1987; 38937; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Ship Plans (1876-1980s))
- Oversize Materials, 1987-1988; 38938; 0.010; Friday, Joe D., Jr. (Folder Oversize Materials)